<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"><metadata>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>City of Asheville</origin>
<pubdate>20100616</pubdate>
<title>Asheville Parks</title>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Asheville, NC</pubplace>
<publish>City of Asheville, NC</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>Server=coa-gisdb-msql; Service=sde:sqlserver:coa-gisdb-msql; Database=GIS; Version=SDE.DEFAULT</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>This data set represents all of the parks managed by the City of Asheville.</abstract>
<purpose>The purpose of the parks data is to allow for general mapping and analysis related to parks in Asheville.</purpose>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20100506</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>In work</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>
-82.614715</westbc>
<eastbc>
-82.476493</eastbc>
<northbc>
35.629556</northbc>
<southbc>
35.469469</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>transit</themekey>
<themekey>bus</themekey>
<themekey>transportation</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>Asheville</placekey>
<placekey>North Carolina</placekey>
<placekey>Buncombe</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>This data has been developed using public funds. The data is therefore in the public domain. Requestors agree that they will not sell this data, will not sell access to the data, nor will they provide for such to be sold except as allowed in NC General Statutes Chapter 132. As a condition of providing electronic GIS data, the City of Asheville reserves the right to require that the data requester agree in writing that the data will not be resold or otherwise used for trade or commercial purposes. The City of Asheville reserves the right to license clients to reproduce GIS data for royalty fees based on the resale of the data and or based on a reciprocal agreement of products, services, or data.</accconst>
<useconst>The City of Asheville acquires, develops, maintains and uses GIS data in support of its internal business functions and the public services it provides.  The GIS data which the City of Asheville distributes and to which it provides access may not be suitable for other purposes or uses.  It is the requestor's responsibility to verify any information derived from the GIS data before making any decisions or taking any actions based on the information.

The City of Asheville shall not be held liable for any errors in the GIS data.  This includes errors of omission, commission, errors concerning the content of the data, and relative and positional accuracy of the data.   Source information used for these data may have been collected at different scales, times or definitions, resulting in inconsistencies among features represented together on this map.  Primary sources from which these data were compiled must be consulted for verification of information contained in the data.  The City of Asheville will not re-distribute data developed from other organizations.  Parcel data was prepared for the inventory of real property found within this jurisdiction, and is compiled from recorded deeds, plats, and other public records and data.   Users of the data are hereby notified that the aforementioned public primary information sources should be consulted for verification of the information.   The City of Asheville assumes no legal responsibility for this information.  Data are presented using the North Carolina State Plane Coordinate System 1983 North American Datum.  Horizontal measurement units are in feet.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>City of Asheville</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>GIS Analyst - IT Services</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>70 Court Plaza</address>
<city>Asheville</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>28802</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(828) 259-5510</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(828) 259-5509</cntfax>
<cntemail>webgis@ashevillenc.gov</cntemail>
<cntinst>http://www.ashevillenc.gov</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<secinfo>
<secsys>FIPS Pub 199</secsys>
<secclass>No Confidentiality</secclass>
<sechandl>Standard Technical Controls</sechandl>
</secinfo>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.1850</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>The attribute accuracy for the parks is excellent based on a deductive estimate of the attribute entry process. Attributes for this data set are limited to the park name, street number and street name when available, and a "ParkSource" field which indicates the source of data for each park representation.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Logical consistency tested to ensure that all chains intersect at nodes.</logic>
<complete>Data set is complete.</complete>
<posacc>
<horizpa>
<horizpar>No tests were done to verify horizontal accuracy. The horizontal accuracy of the parks is limited by the horizontal accuracy of the source data sets, pimarily the Buncombe County Parcels, 2009 6-inch resolution digital orthophotography, and map data derived from the 2009 Asheville Parks, Recreation, and Cultural Arts Master Plan.</horizpar>
</horizpa>
</posacc>
<lineage>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Buncombe County GIS Division</origin>
<pubdate>20090401</pubdate>
<title>Buncombe County 2009 Digital Orthophotography</title>
<geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Asheville, NC</pubplace>
<publish>Buncombe County GIS Division</publish>
</pubinfo>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>400</srcscale>
<typesrc>disc</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20090401</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>BC_2009_Ortho</srccitea>
<srccontr>2009 digital orthophotography was used to determine the proper location for parks that fall outside of parcel boundaries. Several parks are located with a public right of way so the photography allowed for mapping of these features. This process was done through on-screen digitizing in ArcMap 9.3.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<srcinfo>
<srccite>
<citeinfo>
<origin>Buncombe County GIS Division</origin>
<pubdate>20100601</pubdate>
<title>Buncombe County tax parcel database</title>
</citeinfo>
</srccite>
<srcscale>400</srcscale>
<typesrc>disc</typesrc>
<srctime>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>20100601</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<srccurr>publication date</srccurr>
</srctime>
<srccitea>BC_Parcels</srccitea>
<srccontr>Most Asheville parks follow defined tax parcel boundaries. The tax parcels were therefore used to generate most of the park boundaries as defined by the "ParkSource" attribute.</srccontr>
</srcinfo>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Park boundaries were derived from Buncombe County tax parcel database for most parks. Tax parcel polygons were copied and pasted into the parks database and attributes were then updated to reflect the park name and the source of the park boundary information. Additional park boundaries that fall within the public right of way were then delineated with the assistance of staff from Asheville's Parks, Recreation, and Cultural Arts Department. These were heads-up digitized using 2009 digital orthophotography.</procdesc>
<srcused>BC_Parcels</srcused>
<srcused>BC_2009_Ortho</srcused>
<procdate>20100615</procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>59</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<mapproj>
<mapprojn>Lambert Conformal Conic</mapprojn>
<lambertc>
<stdparll>34.333333</stdparll>
<stdparll>36.166667</stdparll>
<longcm>-79.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>33.750000</latprjo>
<feast>2000000.002617</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</lambertc>
</mapproj>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000028</absres>
<ordres>0.000028</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>survey feet</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
<vertdef>
<altsys>
<altres>1.000000</altres>
<altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
</altsys>
</vertdef>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>
GIS.GIS.Parks</enttypl>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ParkName</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Park Name</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Parks, Recreation, and Cultural Arts Department</attrdefs>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>HOUSENUMBER</attrlabl>
<attrdef>House Number</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Address number associated with park, when available</attrdefs>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>STREETNAME</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Street Name</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Street adjacent to park, when available</attrdefs>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ACRES</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Calculated acreage</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Park acreage calculated from feature geometry</attrdefs>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ParkSource</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Source of park boundary information</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Asheville GIS</attrdefs>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE.area</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE.len</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
</attr>
</detailed>
</eainfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20100616</metd>
<metrd>20110504</metrd>
<metfrd>20120504</metfrd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>City of Asheville</cntorg>
<cntper>GIS Division</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>70 Court Plaza</address>
<city>Asheville</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>28802</postal>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>(828)259-5510</cntvoice>
<cntfax>(828) 259-5509</cntfax>
<cntemail>webgis@ashevillenc.gov</cntemail>
<cntinst>http://www.ashevillenc.gov</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metsi>
<metsc>Unclassified</metsc>
</metsi>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>
