<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"><metadata>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>North Carolina Geological Survey</origin>
<pubdate>200906</pubdate>
<pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
<title>buncosde.BUNCOSDE.landslides</title>
<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
<serinfo>
<sername>Geologic Hazard Map Series</sername>
<issue>4</issue>
</serinfo>
<pubinfo>
<pubplace>Raleigh, NC</pubplace>
<publish>North Carolina Geological Survey</publish>
</pubinfo>
<onlink>\\NROAR06\VOL1\DATA\Landslide\Buncombe\Final Deliverables\landslides.shp</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The Buncombe County slope movement-slope movement deposit (NCSM-SMD) database contains the initiation point locations of slope movements and the central points (centroids) of slope movement deposits in Buncombe County.The NCSM-SMD database includes slope movement and deposit type, location, dimensions, dates, geologic (rock and soil), geomorphic, hydrologic, and other site data for individual slope movements and slope movement deposits where known. Data points are color-coded by type of slope movement (process) or slope movement deposit (deposit).  Information shown in this data layer incorporated or considered the work of Michalek (1968), Mills (1996), Pomeroy (1991), and Otteman (2001).</abstract>
<purpose>These data provide an inventory of slope movements and slope movement deposits in Buncombe County, North Carolina as of 24 August 2009 as part of the Landslide Hazard Mapping program commissioned by the NC General Assembly in the Hurricane Recovery Act of 2005.</purpose>
<supplinf>This data set refers to professional publications in the attribute fields. These publications are:

American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials (AASHTO), 2008, M145-91 (2008), Standard specification for classification of soils and soil-aggregate mixtures for highway construction purposes.

American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials (AASHTO), 2007, T297-94 (2007), Standard method of test for consolidated, undrained triaxial compression test on cohesive soils; ASTM Designation: D 4767-88e1

American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM) D 2488-84, 1984, Standard practice for description and identification of soils (visual-manual procedure), in Annual Book of ASTM Standards, v. 04.08.

American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM) D2487-85, 1985, Standard test method for classification of soils for engineering purposes, in Annual Book of ASTM Standards, v. 04.08.

Clark, G.M., 1987, Debris slide and debris flow historical events in the Appalachians south of the glacial border, in Costa, J.E., and Wieczorek, G.F., eds., Debris flows/avalanches:  process, recognition, and mitigation:  Geological Society of America Reviews in Engineering Geology v. VII, p. 125-138.

Cruden, D.M. and Varnes, D.J., 1996, Landslide types and processes, in Turner, A.K., and Schuster, R.L., eds., Landslides - Investigation and mitigation: Transportation Research Board Special Report No. 247, National Research Council, National Academy Press, Washington, D.C., p. 36-75.

Eschner, A.R. and Patric, J.H., 1982, Debris avalanches in eastern upland forests: Journal of Forestry, v. 80, p. 343-347.

Hack, J.T. and Goodlett, J.C., 1960, Geomorphology and forest ecology of a mountain region in the Central Appalachians:  U.S. Geological Survey Professional Paper 347, 66 p.

Hales, T.C., Hwang, T., Band, L., Ford, C., and Vose, J.M., 2007, Long term adjustment of canopy root depth and strength:  Implications for catchment hydrology and slope stability:  Eos Transaction, American Geophysical Union, v. 88, no. 52, Fall Meeting Supplement, H31G-0741.

Hales, T.C., Ford, C.R., Hwang, T., Vose, J., and Band, L.E., Topographic and ecologic controls on root reinforcement: Journal of Geophysical Research doi: 10.1029/2008JF001168, in press.

Hammond, C., Hall, D., Miller, S., and Swetik, P., 1992, Level I stability analysis (LISA) documentation for Version 2.0: General Technical Report INT-285, U. S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Intermountain Research Station, 190 p.

Hewlett, J.D., Fortson, J.C., and Cunningham, G.B., 1984, Additional tests on the effect of rainfall intensity on storm flow and peak flow from wild-land basins: Water Resources Research, v. 20, no.7, p. 985-989.

Klein, C. and Hurlbut, C.S., 1985, Manual of mineralogy (after J.D. Dana):  20th edition, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 596 p.

Jackson, J.A., ed., 1997, Glossary of geology:  4th edition, American Geological Institute, 769 p.

Merschat, C.E., and Cattanach, B.L., 2007, Bedrock geologic map of Buncombe County, North Carolina:  N. C. Geological Survey, scale 1:62,500, unpublished.

Michalek, D.D., 1968, Fanlike features and related periglacial phenomena of the southern Blue Ridge [Ph.D. dissertation]:  Chapel Hill, University of North Carolina, 198 p.

Mills, H. H., 1996, Map of surficial deposits, northeast quarter of the Weaverville 7.5-minute quadrangle, North Carolina:  N. C. Geological Survey Open-File Report 96-4, scale 1:24,000.

Neary, D.G. and Swift, L.W., 1987, Rainfall thresholds for triggering a debris avalanching event in the southern Appalachian Mountains, in Costa, J.E., and Wieczorek, G.F., eds., Debris flows/avalanches - Process, recognition and mitigation:  Geological Society of America, Reviews in Engineering Geology, v. VII, p. 81-92.

North Carolina Geological Survey, 1985, Geologic map of North Carolina:  N. C. Geological Survey, scale 1:500,000.  Out of print.  Available at: http://gis.enr.state.nc.us/sid/bin/index.plx?client=zGeologic_Maps&amp;site=9AM

Otteman, R.A., 2001, Using GIS to model debris flow susceptibility for the Bent Creek Experimental Forest near Asheville, North Carolina [M.S. thesis]:  Greenville, Eastern Carolina University, 181 p.

Pack, R.T., Tarboton, D.G., and Goodwin, C.N., 1998, Terrain stability mapping with SINMAP, technical description and users guide for version 1.00:  Terratech Consulting Ltd., Salmon Arm, B.C., Canada, Report Number 4114-0, 68 p.

Pomeroy, J.S., 1991, Map showing late 1977 debris avalanches southwest of Asheville, western North Carolina: U.S. Geological Survey Open-File Report 91-334, scale 1:24,000, 25 p. text.

United States Department of Agriculture, 2008, Soil survey geographic (SSURGO) database for Buncombe County, North Carolina: U.S. Department of Agriculture, Natural Resources Conservation Service.  Available at: http://SoilDataMart.nrcs.usda.gov/.

Varnes, D.J., 1978, Slope movement types and processes, in Landslide analysis and control, Schuster, R.L., and Krizak, R.J. (eds.), National Research Council Transportation Research Board Special Report No. 176,p. 11-33.

Wieczorek, G.F., Mossa, G.S., and Morgan, B.A., 2004, Regional debris flow distribution and preliminary risk assessment from severe storm events in the Appalachian Blue Ridge Province, USA:  Landslides, v. 1, p. 53-59.

Williamson, D.A., 1984, Unified rock classification system:  Bulletin of the Association of Engineering Geologists, vol. XXI, no. 3, p. 345-354.

Witt, A.C., 2005, A brief history of debris flow occurrence in the French Broad River watershed, western North Carolina: The North Carolina Geographer, v. 13, p. 58-82.

Wooten, R.M. and Latham, R.S., 2004, Report on the May 5-7, 2003 debris flows on slopes underlain by sulfidic bedrock of the Wehutty, Nantahala, and Copper Hill Formations, Swain County, North Carolina: N. C. Geological Survey report of investigation (to Swain County Emergency Management and Building Inspections Department), 12 p.

Wooten, R.M., Latham, R.S., Witt, A.C., Fuemmeler, S.J., Gillon, K.A., Douglas, T.J., and Bauer, J.B., 2006, Slope movement hazard maps of Macon County, North Carolina: N.C. Geological Survey Geologic Hazards Map Series 1, 3 sheets, map scale 1:48,000.

Wooten, R.M., Witt, A.C., Gillon, K.A., Douglas, T.J., Latham, R.S., Fuemmeler, S.J., Bauer, J.B., 2008, Slope movement hazard maps of Watauga County, North Carolina: N.C. Geological Survey Geologic Hazards Map Series 3, 4 sheets, map scale 1:36,000.

Wooten, R.M., Witt, A.C., Gillon, K.A., Douglas, T.J., Fuemmeler, S.J., Bauer, J.B., Latham, R.S, 2009, Slope movement hazard maps of Watauga County, North Carolina: N.C. Geological Survey Geologic Hazards Map Series 4, 3 sheets, map scale 1:54,000.

List of abbreviations:

ASU:  Appalachian State University
DEM:  Digital elevation model
DOQQ:  Digital ortho quarter quandrangle
EBCI:  Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians
EM:  Emergency Management
Ft:  foot or feet
FHWA:  Federal Highway Administration
GIS:  Geographic Information System
HRD:  Highlands Ranger District
IZ:  Initiation Zone
LiDAR:  Light Detecting and Ranging
LQS:  North Carolina Department of Environment and Natural Resources Land Quality Section
Med:  Medium
MVSD:  Maggie Valley Sanitation District
NCCGIA:  North Carolina Center for Geographic Information Analysis
NCDEM:  North Carolina Division of Emergency Management
NCDOT:  North Carolina Department of Transportation
NCGS:  North Carolina Geological Survey
NPS:  National Park Service
NRCS:  Natural Resources Conservation Service
TIMS:  NCDOT Traveler Information Management System
USFS: United States Forest Service
USGS:  United States Geological Survey

Glossary of commonly used terms:

The glossary contains the definitions of terms as used in this document and the slope movement hazard maps and datasets. Unless otherwise noted, these definitions are in general accordance with, or based in part on, definitions contained in Jackson (1997) and Cruden and Varnes (1996).

A

actinolite:  A green mineral of the amphibole group, a hydrous calcium-iron-magnesium silicate.

alluvium:  Clay, silt, sand, gravel or similar unconsolidated detrital earthen material deposited during relatively recent geologic time by a stream or other body of running water. Alluvium usually contains rounded particles and usually collects in the channels and floodplains of creeks, streams, rivers, and lakes.

almandine:  The iron-aluminum end member of the garnet group, characterized by a deep red to purplish color.

AmoozemeterT:  A constant head permeameter used to measure the in-place saturated hydraulic conductivity of soil in the unsaturated zone in the field.

amphibole:  A group of generally dark hydrous silicate minerals including common rock-forming varieties such as hornblende and actinolite.

amphibolite:  A type of dark metamorphic rock consisting mainly of amphibole and plagioclase feldspar with little or no quartz.

anticline:  A fold in which, in map view, the oldest layers of rock are in the core.  Usually, the layers are bent convex upward to form an arch, in contrast to a syncline.

apex:  The uppermost and usually narrowest part of a debris fan deposit nearest the source area of the fan.

arkose:   A type of feldspar-rich sandstone commonly derived from rapid disintegration of granitic rocks.

artesian:  An adjective referring to groundwater confined under hydrostatic pressure.

artesian discharge:  Discharge of water from a well, spring, seep, or aquifer by artesian pressure.

Atterberg limits:  In a sediment (e.g., soil) the water-content boundaries between the semiliquid and plastic states (known as the liquid limit) and between the plastic and semisolid states (known as the plastic limit).

augen:  German word meaning "eyes" used to describe lenticular-shaped minerals in metamorphic rocks.  See porphyroblast.

auger:  A screw-like, rotary boring tool used to advance into soil or other unconsolidated near-surface material.  Small augers can be advanced by hand; large augers are usually mechanically driven by drilling rigs.

azimuth:  Bearing of a linear geologic structure measured in a vertical plane that passes through the structure.

B

basalt:  A mafic extrusive rock consisting of iron and magnesium silicate minerals and plagioclase feldspar.

basement:  The oldest rocks that underlie all other rocks in the area.

basin (sedimentary):  A low area of the Earth's crust in which sediments may accumulate.

bearing:  The horizontal direction of a line on the Earth's surface with reference to the cardinal points of the compass.

bedding:  The arrangement of sedimentary rock into layers of various thicknesses; also referred to as stratification.

biotite:  A black, dark-brown or dark-green potassium, iron and magnesium-bearing mineral of the mica group.

block field:  An accumulation of boulders or angular blocks of rock, generally with little or no fine sediment and without a cliff or a ledge upslope as an apparent source. Block fields usually occur on high mountain slopes where they are most extensive along slopes parallel to contour.

block stream:  A linear accumulation of boulders or angular blocks of rock, generally with little or no fine sediment and without a cliff or a ledge upslope as an apparent source. Block streams usually occur at heads of ravines and as narrow bodies more extensive downslope than along slope.

blowout:  A type of slope failure in which water and material bursts forth from the ground and then proceeds downslope as overland flow.  Blowouts are possibly caused by excessive pore water pressure (Hack and Goodlett, 1960).

boulder:  A detached rock mass larger than a cobble, having a diameter greater than 12 inches (ASTM 2487-85, 1985).

brittle fault:  A displacement or offset within a rock mass characterized by brittle (non-plastic) behavior evidenced by angular broken rock fragments or minerals.

C

calc-silicate granofels:  A metamorphic rock consisting mainly of calcium-bearing silicate minerals.

calcareous:  A rock or sediment that is rich in calcium carbonate.

calcite:  A common white or colorless rock-forming mineral, calcium carbonate.

carbonaceous:  A rock or sediment that is rich in carbon or organic matter.

chalcopyrite: A bright, brass-yellow tetragonal mineral: CuFeS2

chlorite:  A group of green, platy, hydrous iron-magnesium, aluminum silicate minerals, resembling and often associated with minerals of the mica group (Klein and Hurlbut, 1985).

clastic:  A rock or sediment composed of fragments derived from pre-existing rocks or minerals and transported by wind, water, or ice.

clay: 1) A fine-grained soil, with particles having a diameter less than 0.003 inches, that can be made to exhibit plasticity within a range of water contents and that exhibits considerable strength when air dry (ASTM 2487-85, 1985). 2) Any mineral occurring in the clay-sized fraction of a soil, a suspension, or a rock, with the understanding that size imposes physical and chemical characteristics.  For the most part, such "clays" are hydrous aluminosilicate or phyllosilicate minerals belonging to the clorite, illite, kaolin, or smectite clay groups (Klein and Hurlbut, 1985).

cleavage:  In rocks, the property or tendency to split along aligned fractures, minerals, or other closely spaced planar structures or textures, produced by deformation or metamorphism; in minerals, the tendency to break along planes of inherent weakness in the crystal structure.

coalesce (coalescing):  A term used to describe landforms that join or merge, e.g., coalescing debris fans.

cobble:  A rock fragment larger than a pebble and smaller than a boulder, having a diameter in the range of 3 inches to 12 inches (ASTM 2487-85, 1985).

cohesion:  Shear strength component of a soil (sediment), rock, or other intact solid related to mineral grain bonding and not particle friction.

colluvium:  A general term applied to any loose, heterogeneous, and unconsolidated mass of soil and rock particles deposited by rainwash, sheetwash, mass wasting, or slow, continuous downslope creep. Colluvium usually contains angular to subrounded rock particles and usually collects at the base or other low gradient portions of slopes or hillsides.

composite:  a type of slope movement in which different types of movement occur in different areas of the displaced mass, sometimes simultaneously.

compositional layering:  An outcrop- or hand sample-scale structure in metamorphic rocks produced by subparallel layers of various origins that cannot be confidently identified as bedding.

conglomerate:  A sedimentary rock consisting of gravel-sized, round water worn fragments of rock cemented together by another mineral substance.

contact zone:  A zone surrounding an igneous intrusion in which the surrounding country rock shows the effects of increased heat during metamorphism.

contact:  A surface forming the boundary between rocks of different types and/or ages.

creep:  The slow, more or less continuous downslope movement of mineral, rock, and soil particles by gravity.

crenulations:  Small-scale folds or crinkles with wavelengths generally less than one inch. Crenulations may occur along the cleavage planes of a rock that has undergone structural deformation.

cross-bedding:  In a sedimentary deposit, an arrangement of inclined layers between the main bedding planes.

crust:  The outermost layer of the Earth.

crystalline:  An interlocking arrangement of mineral crystals in igneous or metamorphic rocks.

cut slope:  A slope exposed by excavating earth materials.

D

debris: A soil that contains a significant proportion of coarse material; 20 to 80 percent of the particles are greater than coarse sand (0.08 inches or 2 millimeters), with the remainder finer than 0.08 inches or 2 millimeters.

debris fan:  A deposit of debris-sized material that is known or reasonably inferred to be emplaced by mass wasting processes and has a distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape.  Debris fan can include colluvial and alluvial components.

debris flow:  A type of slope movement in which the displaced mass is composed of debris and the water content in the displaced mass is sufficient for the material to liquefy and resemble a viscous fluid.

debris slide:  A slope movement initiated by slippage along a well-defined failure surface that is usually planar or curvi-planar in which the displaced mass is composed of debris. Slides are divided into two classes, rotational and translational. Slides usually consist of displaced and deformed blocks of material.

debris slide, flow:  A slope movement with characteristics of a debris slide and a debris flow. A slope movement that likely begins as a debris slide and then mobilizes into a debris flow once sufficient water is available.

debris undifferentiated:  A deposit of debris sized material that is known or reasonably inferred to be emplaced by mass wasting processes but lacks the distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape of a debris fan.

deformation:  A general term for the process of folding, faulting, shearing, compression or extension of the rocks as a result of various Earth forces.

dendritic:  1) A mineral that has crystallized in a branching pattern. 2) A drainage pattern in which the streams branch randomly in all directions.

deposit:  Earth, debris, or rock material that has accumulated from a past slope movement or movements, but not necessarily identified as being associated with a specific known slope movement event or events.

deposition:  The process by which material such as sediment is laid down by natural agents such as water, air, and ice.

diabase:  A dark, medium-grained, plutonic igneous rock consisting mostly of calcium-rich feldspar and mafic minerals.

differential weathering:  Weathering that occurs at different rates, as a result of variations in composition and resistance of a rock or differences in intensity of weathering, and usually results in an uneven surface where more resistant material stands higher or protrudes above softer or less resistant parts.

dike:  A tabular igneous intrusion that cuts across the bedding or foliation of the rock surrounding it.

diorite:  A type of plutonic igneous rock composed of plagioclase feldspar and one or more dark minerals, including biotite mica, hornblende, or pyroxene.  Feldspar is more abundant than the dark minerals, giving the rock a characteristic "salt and pepper" appearance.

dip:  The angle (0-90 degrees) that a stratum or any planar feature (e.g., bedding, fault plane or foliation) makes with the horizontal, measured perpendicular to the strike of the feature and within a vertical plane.

dip slope:  A slope of the land surface, roughly determined by and conforming with, the direction and angle of the dip of foliation or bedding of the underlying rock.

dolomite:  A common white or colorless rock-forming mineral, calcium magnesium carbonate; also a rock composed of this mineral; adj.: dolomitic.

ductile fault:  A displacement or offset within a rock mass characterized by plastic (non-brittle) behavior of rock and mineral fragments evidenced by elongated, non-angular rock fragments and minerals (e.g., mylonite).

E

earth:  A soil in which approximately 80 percent or more of the particles are smaller than 0.08 inches (2 millimeters).

earth fan:  A deposit of earth sized material that is known or reasonably inferred to be emplaced by mass wasting processes and has a distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape.

earth flow:  A type of slope movement in which the displaced mass is composed of earth and the water content in the displaced mass is sufficient for the material to liquefy and resemble a viscous fluid.

earth slide:  A slope movement initiated by slippage along a well-defined failure surface that is usually planar or curvi-planar in which the displaced mass is composed of earth.

earth undifferentiated:  A deposit of earth sized material that is known or reasonably inferred to be emplaced by mass wasting processes but lacks a distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape.

embankment:  Soil, rock fragments, and other materials put in place by humans and used to extend a side slope or a land surface for a roadway or building site, or to build up low-lying land, hold back water (e.g., dam), or fill in an enclosed space (e.g., mine workings).  Synonymous with man-made fill, but distinguished from naturally occurring, sedimentary fill.

emplacement:  A term used in describing the process of intrusion of a plutonic igneous rock.

eon: The longest geologic time unit, consisting of eras and their subordinate time units, i.e., periods and epochs.   Another use of the term is to denote one billion years.

epidote:  A green silicate mineral, hydrous calcium aluminum-iron silicate, common in certain metamorphic rocks.

epoch:  The unit of geologic time into which a period is divided.

era:  The unit of geologic time intermediate between an eon and a period; e.g., the Paleozoic Era.

erosion: The general process or group of processes that act upon the materials of the Earth's crust by loosening, dissolving or wearing them away, then moving them from one place to another by natural agencies such as wind, gravity, or water.

escarpment:  A long, more or less continuous cliff or relatively steep slope facing in one general direction, breaking the continuity of the land by separating two levels of gently sloping surfaces, that is produced by erosion or faulting (e.g., Blue Ridge Escarpment).

exfoliation:  The process of mechanical weathering of igneous and metamorphic rocks by which concentric scales, plates, or shells of variable thickness are successively spalled or stripped from the bare surface of a rock mass.

extrusive:  A volcanic igneous rock that has been erupted onto the surface of the Earth; e.g., a lava flow.

F

fall:  A type of slope movement in which material abruptly breaks off or detaches from a steep slope or cliff surface. Little or no sliding (shear displacement) along the failure surface is involved, and the detached material descends mostly through the air by free fall, bouncing, or rolling (Varnes, 1987).

fan undifferentiated:  A deposit of unknown grain size that has a distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape.

fault:  A fracture or a zone of fractures along which the rock on one side has been displaced relative to the rock on the other side.

feldspar:  A group of widespread aluminum-silicate minerals containing oxides of sodium, calcium, or potassium, which constitute 60 percent of the rocks of the Earth's crust.  Feldspar minerals occur as components of most rock types, especially igneous and metamorphic rocks.

feldspathic:  A rock or other mineral aggregate containing feldspar.

felsic:  An igneous or metamorphic rock having abundant light colored minerals (chiefly feldspar and quartz) in its composition; also, said of those minerals.

fill: Soil, rock fragments, and other materials put in place by humans. Distinguished from naturally occurring, sedimentary fill.

flow:  A type of slope movement in which the water content in the displaced mass is sufficient for the material to liquefy and behave as a viscous fluid.

fold:  A product of deformation resulting in a curve or bend of a planar structure such as rock strata, bedding planes, foliation, or cleavage.

foliation:  The planar arrangement of textural or structural features in a metamorphic rock that results from flattening or alignment of the constituent mineral grains such as mica.

foot slope:  The lower gentle slope of a hillside below a steep rock face or escarpment including lower slopes of diminishing steepness; used here to generally designate the lower third of a hillslope.

formation:  A body of rock identified by its unique lithologic characteristics and stratigraphic position recognized as a stratigraphic unit for purposes of geologic mapping.

fracture:  A general term for any break in a rock, whether or not it causes displacement, due to mechanical failure by stress  (usually a planar joint or fault surface).

G

garnet:  A group of mostly isometric (equant, or grain like) shaped silicate minerals with glassy luster, high hardness, no cleavage.  Found in a wide variety of igneous and metamorphic rocks, their colors typically range in color from red, purple, and black, to green, yellow, and cinnamon brown.  Compositionally, the specific mineral species range those containing magnesim, iron, or manganese (all with lesser aluminum), and those containing calcium (with lesser aluminum, iron or chromium. (Klein and Hurlbut, 1985).

garnetiferous: Containing garnet.

geographic information system (GIS):  A computer application used to store, view, and analyze geographical information, especially maps.

geologic map:  A two-dimensional representation of the Earth's surface on which is recorded geologic information such as the distribution, nature, and age relationships of rock units and the occurrence of structural features, mineral deposits, and fossil localities.

geologic cross section:  A diagram or drawing that shows features on a geologic map, as they would appear at depth in a vertical section through the Earth.

geomorphic:  Pertaining to the landforms that develop on the surface of the Earth.

geomorphology: The study of the classification, description, nature, origin, and development of landforms and their relationships to underlying structures, and of the history of geologic changes as recorded by these surface features.

gneiss:  A foliated rock, usually formed by regional metamorphism, in which bands or layers of granular minerals alternate with bands or layers in which minerals having flaky or elongate prismatic habits predominate.

graded bedding:  A type of layering in sedimentary deposits in which each layer displays a gradual change in particle size, usually from coarse at the base to fine at the top.

granite:  A common light-colored, coarse-grained plutonic igneous rock consisting of variable amounts of quartz, feldspar, and accessory minerals.

granodiorite:  A type of plutonic igneous rock in which two or more varieties of feldspar are accompanied by quartz and smaller amounts of dark minerals such as biotite mica and hornblende.

granofels:  A metamorphic rock with a texture that is neither foliated nor lineated.

gravel:  An unconsolidated, natural accumulation of rock fragments resulting from erosion and consisting predominantly of particles larger than sand but smaller than cobbles greater than 0.19 inches and smaller than 3 inches (ASTM 2487-85, 1985).

graywacke: A typically light to dark grey, poorly sorted sandstone in which coarser fragments of rocks and minerals are cemented together by fine-grained material, much of which consists of clay minerals.

ground water:  Water below the surface of the Earth. Also spelled: groundwater, ground-water.

H

head:  The upper parts of the slope movement material in contact between the displaced material and the main scarp.

hematite:  A common iron mineral occurring in metallic-looking, steel-gray or iron-black rhombohedral crystals, in reniform masses or fibrous aggregates, or in deep-red or red-brown earthy forms.  It is the principal ore of iron, and a primary source of the red color of many soils.

hornblende:  The most common mineral of the amphibole group, a complex hydrous aluminum silicate in which calcium, sodium, iron, and magnesium are present in varying amounts; commonly black, dark-green or brown and occurring in distinct long, slender crystals or in columnar, fibrous or granular forms.  It is a primary constituent of many felsic and intermediate igneous rocks, and while less common in mafic igneous rocks, and it is a common constituent in metamorphosed mafic rocks, such as amphibolite.

hummock:  A rounded or conical knoll, mound, hillock, or other small elevation.  Also, a slight rise of the ground above a level surface. adj. hummocky:  abounding in hummocks, or uneven.

hydraulic conductivity: The capacity of soil, sediment or rock to transmit water.  It is expressed as the volume of water that will move in unit time under a unit hydraulic gradient through a unit area measured at right angles to the direction of flow (e.g., gallons per day, meters per day). syn. permeability coefficient.

hydrous:  A mineral compound containing water.

I

igneous rock:  A rock that solidified from molten or partly molten silicate material, i.e., from a magma.

imbrication:  A sedimentary fabric characterized by disk-shaped or elongate rock fragments arranged in an overlapping manner that indicates transport and deposition by sediment-water mixtures such as in a debris flow.

initiation zone:  The area of a hill slope inferred to be the location where a debris flow or other shallow translational slope movement begins. It is usually bounded in the upslope direction by the main scarp, and exposes the lower boundary of displaced material (surface of rupture) originally below the ground surface.  Also referred to as the source area in some literature.

interlayer:  A layer situated between others of a different nature.

internal friction:  The part of the shear strength of a soil (sediment), rock  or other intact solid that depends on the magnitude of the normal stresses on the potential shear surface, measured as an angle and given as the internal angle of friction.

intrusive:  Pertaining to intrusion, the process of emplacement (injection) of magma in pre-existing rock; also the igneous rock mass so formed within the surrounding rock mass.

J

jarosite:  An ochre-yellow or brown group of minerals consisting of hydrous iron sulfates.

joint:  A fracture, crack or parting in a rock, without displacement (see fracture).

K

kaolin:  The name given to a group of hydrous aluminum silicate clay minerals that share a particular crystal structure, all of them derived from the alteration of feldspar and mica.

knickpoint:  An interruption or break in slope where the longitudinal profile of a stream or valley changed abruptly.

L

lamination: A rock fabric that consists of very thin layering in metamorphic and sedimentary rocks.

landslide:  An informal term for a wide variety of mass movements and processes involving the downslope transport, under gravitational influence, of soil and rock material en masse. The term "slope movement", rather than "landslide" (Varnes, 1987), is preferred by the NCGS in order to include all mechanisms of slope movement by flowing, falling, or sliding.

lava flow:  Molten volcanic material poured out onto the surface of the Earth; also a solidified extrusive igneous rock.

lens   A mineral deposit or body of rock that is thick in the middle and thins out towards the edges, like a convex lens.

LiDAR:  Topographic data obtained by a Light Detecting And Ranging method (airborne laser altimetry) and provided by the North Carolina Floodplain Mapping Program at 6 m pixel resolution.

limestone : A sedimentary rock consisting predominantly of calcium carbonate.

limonite:  The name given to a group of brown non-crystalline hydrous iron oxides formed by weathering of iron minerals.

lineation:  A linear structure in a rock formed by aligned minerals or intersecting planes.

liquid limit:  The water-content boundary between the semiliquid and the plastic states of a sediment (e.g., soil).  It is one of the Atterberg limits.

lithification:  To change to stone, or to petrify; especially to consolidate from loose sediment to a solid rock.

lithology:  The description of rocks, especially in hand specimen and in outcrop, on the basis of such characteristics as color, mineral composition, and grain size.

lithosphere:  A layer of the Earth characterized by strength relative to the underlying asthenosphere.  It includes the crust and upper part of the mantle, and is in the order of 60 miles in thickness.

lineament:   A linear topographic feature that is believed to reflect crustal (i.e., bedrock) structure.  Examples are fault lines, fracture zones, straight stream courses, and linear ridgelines.

lobate:  Lobe shaped, i.e., having a rounded, elongate shape.

M

mafic:  An igneous or metamorphic rock composed chiefly of one or more ferromagnesian, dark-colored minerals; also, said of those minerals.

mantle:  The zone, layer, or shell of the Earth below the crust and above the core.

marble:  A metamorphic rock consisting predominantly of fine- to coarse-grained recrystallized calcite and/or dolomite.

matrix:  The finer-grained material enclosing or filling the interstices between, the larger grains or particles of sediment or sedimentary rock. Also the finer-grained groundmass of an igneous or metamorphic rock.

megacryst: See porphyroblast.

meta: A prefix that indicates that a rock has been metamorphosed, used with the name of a sedimentary or igneous rock, e.g., metabasalt, metaquartzite, metagraywache, metaconglomerate, metadiabase.

metaigneous rock:  A metamorphosed igneous rock.

metamorphic rock:  A rock derived from metamorphism of a pre-existing rock.

metamorphism:  Recrystallization of solid rock at variable temperatures and/or pressures below the Earth's surface producing changes in the rock's texture or composition.

metasedimentary rock:  A metamorphosed sedimentary rock.

midslope:  The middle third of a slope proportioned approximately from ridge top to toe slope.

mica:  A group of hydrous aluminum-rich silicate minerals, all of which have perfect basal cleavage that allows them to be peeled apart in thin layers (e.g., muscovite, biotite).

micaceous:  A term describing a mica-rich rock.

migmatite:  A metamorphic rock showing localized melting of light-colored materials.

mineral:  A naturally occurring, inorganic substance having an orderly internal crystalline structure, characteristic chemical composition, and physical properties.

modified slope:  a slope that has been significantly altered by humans by construction activities (such as roads, cuts, fills, etc.).

monadnock:  A hill or mountain above the general level of the land representing an isolated remnant in an area that has been largely beveled flat by erosion.

morphology: [geomorphology] The shape of the earth's surface.

mud:  A mixture of fine silt-and clay-sized particles.

mudstone: A sedimentary rock composed of consolidated fine silt- and clay-sized particles.

muscovite: A transparent to silvery colored potassium-bearing mineral of the mica group.

mylonite: Any foliated and usually lineated, fine grained metamorphic rock which shows evidence of strong ductile deformation related to movements along a ductile fault zone.

N

nonconformity:  An unconformity between stratified rocks above and older igneous or metamorphic rocks below.

normal fault:  A fault in which the hanging wall has moved downward relative to the footwall.

O

oblique slope:  A relatively steeper face of a hillslope, facing in a direction at an angle to the dip of the rock layers. An oblique slope faces a direction that lies between a dip slope and a scarp slope.

olivine:  An olive-green to brown iron-and magnesium-rich silicate mineral, common in mafic and very mafic igneous rocks.

other -  The reported location of an unspecified slope movement that has yet to be field verified (North Carolina Geological Survey informal definition).

outcrop:  Rock that is exposed at the surface of the Earth.

oxide:  A compound of oxygen with an element.

P

Paleozoic: The first of three eras of the Phanerozoic Eon, lasting from about 570 to 240 million years ago.

pebble:  A general term for a small, rounded, water-worn stone; specifically, a rock fragment larger than sand and smaller than a cobble, having a diameter in the range of 0.16 inches to 2.5 inches (4 millimeters to 64 millimeters).

pegmatite:  An exceptionally coarse-grained, light-colored intrusive igneous rock, with interlocking crystals of quartz, feldspar, and mica, usually found as irregular dikes, lenses or veins, especially at the margins of large bodies of plutonic igneous rock.

period:  A geologic time unit intermediate in rank between an era and an epoch.

permeameter:  An instrument used to measure permeability (see AmoozemeterT).

plastic limit:  The water-content boundary range of a sediment (e.g., soil) between the plastic and semisolid states.  It is one of the Atterberg limits.

plunge:  The inclination from horizontal of a linear structure, measured in the vertical plane.

pod:  A metamorphic rock that is long in one dimension and short in two dimensions with its long axis most commonly parallel to layering.

porphyroblast:  A large crystal developed in a metamorphic rock by recrystallization.

pore water:  Subsurface water in the voids of rock, sediment, or soil.

process:  A slope movement or landslide.

Proterozoic: That eon of geologic time represented by rocks in which there is little evidence of life (fossils), comprising three eras: Early, Middle, Late - from about 2,500 million to 570 million years ago.

protolith: The parent rock of a metamorphic rock.

pyrite: A common, pale-bronze or brass yellow, cubic-shaped mineral composed of iron and sulfur; also commonly referred to as "fools gold".

pyrrhotite: A common red-brown to bronze hexagonal to pseudohexagonal mineral: Fe1-xS.

Q

quadrangle:  A rectangular area bounded by parallels of latitude and meridians of longitude. In this database, "quadrangle" means a USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle map, 1:24,000 scale.

quartz: A very common rock-forming mineral consisting of silicon dioxide.

quartzite: A granular metamorphic rock derived form sandstone and consisting of interlocking grains of quartz.

R

recrystallization: The formation of new crystalline mineral grains in the solid state by metamorphism.

recharge:   The amount of water added to the zone of saturation;  also the processes involved in the absorption or addition of water to the zone of saturation (e.g., infiltration).

residuum:  An unconsolidated or partly weathered, parent material soil, that developed in place by the physical and chemical weathering from the consolidated rock on which it lies.

rift:  A long narrow continental trough that is bounded by normal faults.  It marks a zone along which the entire thickness of the lithosphere has ruptured under extension.

rock:  An aggregate of one or more minerals, or a body of  undifferentiated mineral matter.

rock fall:  A type of slope movement in which a single mass of rock of any size is detached from a steep slope or cliff along a surface on which little or no shear displacement occurs. The detached material descends mostly through the air by free fall, bounding, or rolling.

rock sequence:  A succession of rocks arranged in their relative position and age.

regolith:  A general term for the layer or mantle of fragmental and unconsolidated rock material that nearly everywhere forms the surface of land and overlies or covers bedrock. It includes alluvium, colluvium, residuum, debris, earth, and soil.

rock slide:  A slope movement initiated by slippage along a well-defined failure surface that is usually planar or curvi-planar in which the displaced mass is composed of rock that was intact and in its natural place before the initiation of movement.

rotational movement:  A term used to describe the type of movement in a slide in which the displaced material has moved along a curved, concave upward, (i.e., spoon-shaped) failure surface.

S

sand:  A rock or mineral fragment or a detrital particle of any composition smaller than gravel and larger than a coarse silt grain, having a diameter between 0.003 inches and 0.19 inches  (ASTM 2487-85, 1985).

sandstone:  A sedimentary rock composed chiefly of sand-sized grains cemented by calcium carbonate, silica, or other materials.

scar:  A cliff, precipice, or other steep slope, that corresponds to the zone of depletion, or the area from which a slope movement originated.

scarp:  A rupture of the ground surface with differential vertical displacement. The main scarp is above the head of the slope movement, and usually forms the upper periphery of the displaced mass. A minor scarp occurs within the body of the displaced mass.

scarp slope:  A relatively steeper face of a hillslope, facing in a direction opposite the dip of the rock strata or layers.  This term does not refer to a rupture of the ground surface (see scarp).

schist:  A  typically well foliated metamorphic rock that splits easily into thin layers or slabs because of the well developed parallelism of abundant flat or elongate minerals such as mica and hornblende.

sequence:  A succession of geologic events, processes, or rocks, arranged in chronologic order to show their relative position and age with respect to geologic history as a whole.

sericite:  Very fine-grained muscovite or other white mica.

sediment:  Loose, unconsolidated, fragmental material that originates from weathering of rocks and is transported or deposited by air, water, or ice.

sedimentary rock:  A rock resulting from the consolidation of loose sediment that has accumulated in layers; also a rock formed by precipitation from solution, or an organic rock consisting of the remains or secretions of plants and animals.

sedimentation:  The process of deposition of sediment

shale:  A sedimentary rock composed chiefly of clay and very fine-grained particles of quartz.

shear strength:  The internal resistance of a body to shear stress.

ShelbyT tube:  A 3-inch diameter, thin-walled metal tube used to extract relatively undisturbed soil samples from the subsurface for laboratory testing.

silicate: A mineral whose crystal structure is characterized by a particular arrangement of silicon and oxygen atoms, in which one silicon atoms is set in the middle of a cluster of four oxygen atoms.

silt:  A soil particle less than 0.003 inches in diameter that is non-plastic or very slightly plastic and that exhibits little or no strength when air dry (ASTM 2487-85, 1985).

siltstone: A sedimentary rock composed of silt-sized rock or mineral particles.

slide:  Slides are slope movements initiated by outward or downward rupture of displaced material along a well-defined, typically planar or curvi-planar failure surface. Where the geometry of the failure surface is not obvious or known, the term slide-general is applied. Where obvious or known, the slide is classified as rotational or translational (see slide-rotational and slide-translational).

slide-general: A slide in which the geometry of the failure surface is not obvious or known.

slide-rotational: A slide in which the displaced material experiences rotation (and characteristic backward tilting) as it progresses along a failure surface that is curved and concave upward.

slide-translational: A slide in which the displaced material experiences little to no rotation or backward tilting as it progresses downward along a failure surface that is typically planar.

slope movement:  The gravity-driven gradual or rapid downslope mass movement of soil (earth and/or debris) or rock by falling, flowing, or sliding or by a combination of these movements. The term "slope movement", rather than "landslide" (Varnes, 1987), is preferred by the NCGS in order to include all mechanisms of slope movement by flowing, falling, or sliding.

spread:  A slope movement in which a relatively intact body of material develops lateral fractures and slides over a softer, underlying material.  These often result from liquefaction.

stratification: see bedding.

stratigraphy: A branch of geology concerned with the definition and description of natural divisions of rock strata, including their history and interrelationships with other rocks.

stratum  A sheetlike body or layer of sedimentary rock, visually separable from other layers above and below. The term is more frequently used in its plural form, strata.

strike:  The direction or trend of a planar surface in bedrock, example a bedding, foliation, or fault plane, as it intersects the horizontal.

stringer:  A thin rock or mineral vein occurring in a discontinuous pattern in the host rock.

structure:  A feature in the rock that results from rock deformation.

subsidence:  The sinking or gradual downward settling of the Earth's surface, with little or no horizontal motion.

substrata: rocks in the zone below the surface, whose geologic features, principally stratigraphic and structural, are interpreted on the basis of drill records and various kinds of geophysical evidence rather than by direct observation.

sulfate:  A mineral compound characterized by the presence of SO4.

sulfide:  A mineral compound characterized by joining sulfur with a metal, commonly iron.

sulfidic:  A modifier for a rock that contains a visible component of sulfide minerals (e.g., pyrite, pyrrhotite, chalcopyrite).

surficial deposit:  Unconsolidated and residual, alluvial, colluvial, or glacial deposits lying on bedrock or occurring on the Earth's surface (see regolith).

syncline:  A fold in which, in map view, the youngest layers of rock are in the core.  Generally, the layers are bent concave upward.

synclinorium:  A synclinal structure of regional extent composed of smaller folds.

T

talus:  Rock fragments of any size or shape, usually coarse and angular, derived from and lying at the base of a cliff or very steep rocky slope.  Talus is often a product of rockfall.

tectonic plate: Blocks of oceanic and continental crust and upper mantle, supported by a viscous underlayer of the lower mantle.

tectonics: A branch of geology dealing with the regional assemblage of structural and deformational features of the Earth's crust, and a study of their origins and histories.

tension crack:  A crack or rupture in the ground surface caused by extension or tensile stress but not showing differential vertical displacement. With continued vertical displacement, a tension crack can become a scarp.

thrust fault:  A fault with a dip of 45º or less over much of its extent, on which the hanging (upper) wall appears to have moved upward relative to the footwall (lower).  Horizontal compression  (i.e., crustal shortening) rather than vertical displacement is its characteristic feature.

thrust sheet:  a body of rock that has arrived at its present position by movement along an underlying thrust fault.

toe:  The lowest part of a slope, slope movement or slope movement deposit.

tonalite:  An igneous rock composed chiefly of plagioclase feldspar and quartz, characteristically very low in potassium (see trondhjemite).

topographic map:  A map showing the topographic features of the land surface.

topple:  A slope movement in which material moves forward out of the slope about a point or axis below the center of gravity of the displaced mass.

tourmaline:  A group of varicolored silicate minerals with complex chemical formulas that always include boron and sometimes a little fluorine, commonly in granites and gneisses.

type locality:  The place where the rocks of a geologic unit are described as being representative of the whole unit in a region.

track:  The path of a channelized debris flow between the scar or initiation zone upslope, and the toe or depositional area downslope. The track usually coincides with a pre-existing stream channel or drainage way.

translational movement:  A term used to describe the type of movement in a slide in which the displaced material has moved along a generally planar failure surface (e.g., translational slide).

transmissivity:  The rate at which water is transmitted through a unit width of an aquifer under a unit hydraulic gradient.  It equals the hydraulic conductivity multiplied by the aquifer thickness.

trondhjemite:  An igneous rock composed chiefly of plagioclase feldspar and quartz, characteristically very low in potassium (see tonalite).

U

unconformity:  A surface of erosion or nondeposition in the rock record.

unmodified slope:  A slope that has evolved naturally without any significant alteration by humans (includes timbering and farming, which are not considered significant slope modifying activities).

upper slope:  The upper third of a slope proportioned from the ridge top to the toe slope but excluding the ridge top.

uplift:  A structurally high area in the crust, produced by upward movements that raise or upthrust the rocks as in a dome or arch.

V

vein:  A thin sheet-like mass of rock or mineral that has precipitated from formerly present hydrothermal fluids as they moved through a fracture or fault zone.

W

weathered rock:  A rock that is partly to completely decomposed (Williamson, 1984).  This decomposition is the result of physical and chemical weathering processes.
weathered-rock slide:  A term used to describe a rock slide where the displaced rock is partly- to completely-decomposed (Williamson, 1984) from physical and chemical weathering processes.

weathering:  The physical disintegration and chemical decomposition of rock at the Earth's surface.

window: An area in a thrust sheet where the rocks have been eroded down to the underlying thrust fault, thereby exposing rocks beneath the thrust sheet.

Z

zone of accumulation:  The area of a landslide within which the displaced material lies above the original ground surface.

zone of depletion:  The area of a landslide within which the displaced material lies below the original ground surface.</supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>200906</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>As needed</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc>
-82.883735</westbc>
<eastbc>
-82.172156</eastbc>
<northbc>
35.824183</northbc>
<southbc>
35.422464</southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>landslides</themekey>
<themekey>debris flow</themekey>
<themekey>slope movement</themekey>
<themekey>slope movement deposit</themekey>
<themekey>slope</themekey>
<themekey>hazards</themekey>
<themekey>DEM</themekey>
</theme>
<theme>
<themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt>
<themekey>geoscientific Information</themekey>
<themekey>008</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>North Carolina</placekey>
<placekey>Buncombe County</placekey>
<placekey>NC</placekey>
<placekey>Blue Ridge</placekey>
<placekey>Appalachia</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>Data are available from the North Carolina Geological Survey</accconst>
<useconst>All users of this electronic data set must read and fully comprehend the metadata prior to use. All electronic and/or hardcopy products (maps, data, and text, etc.) produced by the North Carolina Geological Survey landslide hazard assessment program are considered public information (unless otherwise noted) and may be distributed or copied.  When using, distributing or copying this data set as a source, the Originator must be acknowledged. These products are intended to serve for general planning purposes only and are provided on an "as is" basis. This data set shall not be used beyond the limits of the set source scale. This data set does not represent a survey document completed by a licensed land surveyor and should not be utilized as such.</useconst>
<ptcontac>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>North Carolina Geological Survey</cntorg>
<cntper>Rick Wooten</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Senior Geologist for Geohazards and Engineering Geology</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2090 U.S. 70 Highway</address>
<city>Swannanoa</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>28778</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>828.296.4500 ext.4632</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>none</cnttdd>
<cntfax>828.299.7043</cntfax>
<cntemail>Rick.Wooten@ncdenr.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1700 eastern</hours>
<cntinst>Prefer initial contact by e-mail, followed by voice contact.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</ptcontac>
<native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<attracc>
<attraccr>The North Carolina Geological Survery collects and maintains a Microsoft Access database of slope movement and slope movement deposit locations. The database includes rock and soil classification, location information, geomorphic site description and surface and ground water conditions. This information is collected through a combination of field investigation, historical documentation, previously published and unpublished geological data and maps, the interpretation of several vintages of georeferenced and/or orthorectified aerial photography and the interpretation of LiDAR digital elation models by staff geologists.</attraccr>
</attracc>
<logic>Data attributes developed by North Carolina Geological Survey staff geologists. Using Latitude/Longitude values for each record, a XY event theme was created for each record as a point in the Slope Movement database.  The event theme was then converted into a point shapefile in ESRI ArcGIS.</logic>
<complete>These data represent discrete, point locations of known slope movements and slope movement deposits documented by the NCGS. This data set only includes slope movements and slope movement deposits occuring in or depositing into Buncombe County, North Carolina as of August 2009.</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Source information is collected through a combination of field investigation, historical documentation, previously published and unpublished geological data and maps, the interpretation of several vintages of georeferenced and/or orthorectified aerial photography and the interpretation of LiDAR digital elation models by staff geologists. Where site visits were made, NCGS staff visited the location of the landslide to collect detailed information on location, geomorphology, soil and rock properties, and hydrologic conditions at the initiation zones of slope movements or at the apexes of slope movement deposits. All structural measurements were made using Brunton compass unless otherwise noted; all measurements follow right hand rule. This information was collected either in a field notebook, on a landslide field sheet, or in a GPS unit using the best professional judgment of the geologist.  If a site visit was not made, all pertinent information that could be reasonably obtained through a literary source, aerial photography, or LiDAR interpretation was collected. Data is entered into Microsoft Access database.</procdesc>
<procdate>200906</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>North Carolina Geological Survey</cntorg>
<cntper>Richard M. Wooten</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Senior Geologist- Geohazards and Engineering Geology</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2090 U.S. Highway 70</address>
<city>Swannanoa</city>
<state>North Carolina</state>
<postal>28778</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>828.296.4500 ext.4632</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>none</cnttdd>
<cntfax>828.299.7043</cntfax>
<cntemail>rick.wooten@ncmail.net</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1700 eastern</hours>
<cntinst>Prefer initial contact by e-mail, followed by voice contact.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>The Access database is added to ArcMap as a table. Using the Latitude/Longitude values for each record, an XY point event layer was created for each record. The event theme was then exported as a point shapefile in ESRI ArcGIS.</procdesc>
<procdate>200906</procdate>
<proccont>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>North Carolina Geological Survey</cntorg>
<cntper>Richard M. Wooten</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Senior Geologist- Geohazards and Engineering Geology</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2090 U.S. 70 Highway</address>
<city>Swannanoa</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>28778</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>828.296.4500 ext. 4632</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>none</cnttdd>
<cntfax>828.299.7043</cntfax>
<cntemail>rick.wooten@ncmail.net</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1700 eastern</hours>
<cntinst>Prefer initial contact by e-mail, followed by voice contact.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</proccont>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
<srcused>C:\DOCUME~1\acwitt\LOCALS~1\Temp\xml237.tmp</srcused>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Dataset copied.</procdesc>
<srcused>Server=bcgis1; Service=5151; Database=envl; User=envl; Version=sde.DEFAULT</srcused>
</procstep>
<procstep>
<procdesc>Dataset copied.</procdesc>
<srcused>Server=bcgis; Service=sde:sqlserver:bcgis; Database=envl; User=envl; Version=sde.DEFAULT</srcused>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Vector</direct>
<ptvctinf>
<sdtsterm>
<sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
<ptvctcnt>1287</ptvctcnt>
</sdtsterm>
</ptvctinf>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<mapproj>
<mapprojn>Lambert Conformal Conic</mapprojn>
<lambertc>
<stdparll>34.333333</stdparll>
<stdparll>36.166667</stdparll>
<longcm>-79.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>33.750000</latprjo>
<feast>2000000.002617</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</lambertc>
</mapproj>
<planci>
<plance>coordinate pair</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>0.000328</absres>
<ordres>0.000328</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>survey feet</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.257222</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
<vertdef>
<altsys>
<altres>1.000000</altres>
<altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
</altsys>
</vertdef>
</spref>
<eainfo>
<detailed>
<enttyp>
<enttypl>
buncosde.BUNCOSDE.landslides</enttypl>
<enttypd>Locations of slope movements and slope movement deposits in Buncombe County, North Carolina</enttypd>
<enttypds>North Carolina Geological Survey</enttypds>
</enttyp>
<attr>
<attrlabl>NCGSInvs</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The initial or initials of North Carolina Geological Survey investigators</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Initials of Investigator</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>TYPE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>PROJECT</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>QUAD_24K</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>NAME</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SM_MAT</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SM_MECH</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SMD_TYPE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>MVMTDATE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>COL_DATE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>NC_CNTY</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IZLATDD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IZLONGDD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>APXLATDD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>APXLONGDD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ROAD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>RD_AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SA_ASPCT</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DATA_SRC</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LOC_CONF</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>EL_HEAD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>EL_TOE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SLP__CNFG</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>G_POS</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>G_SHAPE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>G_STRUCT</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>D_MASS_L</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>D_MASS_W</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>D_MASS_T</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>TRKLENG</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DAMAGE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>MVMT_HIS</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>UNIT1985</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OTHR_MU</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SRCE_VEG</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ORIGGSL</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH_1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH_2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH_3</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH1MOD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH2MOD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH3MOD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH1MN1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH1MN2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH2MN1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH2MN2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH3MN1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ID</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Internal ascension number.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Internal ascension number.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Type</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The type of entry in the database</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Process</edomv>
<edomvd>A known specific slope movement.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Deposit</edomv>
<edomvd>Earth, debris, or rock material that has accumulated from a past slope movement or movements, but not necessarily identified as being associated with a specific known slope movement event or events.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LITH3MN2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SULLITH1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SULLITH2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SULLITH3</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRAC1AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRAC1DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRAC2AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRAC2DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRAC3AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FRAC3DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BRFLTAZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BRFLTDIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BRFLTTHK</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DLFLTAZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DLFLTDIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DLFLTTHK</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SLBRG</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SLPLUNGE</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FOL1AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FOL1DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FOL2AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FOL2DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FOL3AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Project</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Name of the project for which the data was collected, example Blue Ridge Parkway or Landslide Hazard Mapping</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Name of project</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>FOL3DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Quad_24K</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle name</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Asheville</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Barnardsville</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Bat Cave</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Black Mountain</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Canton</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Craggy Pinnacle</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Cruso</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Dunsmore Mountain</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Enka</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Fines Creek</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Fruitland</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Lake Lure</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Leicester</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Mars Hill</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Moffitt Hill</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Montreat</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Mt. Mitchell</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Oteen</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Sandymush</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Skyland</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Weaverville</edomv>
<edomvd>24k quadrangle name</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CL1DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CL2DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BDG1AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BDG1DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BDG2AZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Name</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The informal geographic name of slope movement designated by NCGS, example Charley Branch #4</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>The informal geographic name of slope movement</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BDG2DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SM_Mat</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The classification of slope movement material. In combination with the slope movement mechanism, this information defines the type of slope movement classified according to Varnes (1978) and Cruden and Varnes (1996).</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Debris, Earth</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement material contains both debris and earth.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Rock, Debris</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement material contains both rock and debris</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Rock, Earth, Debris</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement contains rock, earth and debris</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Debris</edomv>
<edomvd>A soil that contains a significant proportion of coarse material; 20 to 80 percent of the particles are greater than coarse sand (0.08 inches or 2 millimeters), with the remainder finer than 0.08 inches or 2 millimeters.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Earth</edomv>
<edomvd>A soil in which approximately 80 percent or more of the particles are smaller than 0.08 inches (2 millimeters).</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Rock</edomv>
<edomvd>An aggregate of one or more minerals, or a body of  undifferentiated mineral matter.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Jackson, 1997</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Weathered Rock</edomv>
<edomvd>A rock that is partly to completely decomposed (Williamson, 1984).  This decomposition is the result of physical and chemical weathering processes.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Williamson, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IC1DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IC2DIP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OTHER_SD</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1ORGN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1STRUC</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1ASTM</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1MTRX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1MCLR</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1MCLSZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1CLSHP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1CLLI</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1CLWX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1THICK</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL1RELDEN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2ORGN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2STRUC</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2ASTM</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2MTRX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2MCLR</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2MCLSZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2CLSHP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2CLLI</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2CLWX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2THICK</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL2RELDEN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3ORGN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3STRUC</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3ASTM</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3MTRX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3MCLR</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3MCLSZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3CLSHP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3CLLI</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3CLWX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3THICK</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL3RELDEN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4ORGN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4STRUC</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4ASTM</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4MTRX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4MCLR</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4MCLSZ</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4CLSHP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4CLLI</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4CLWX</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4THICK</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SL4RELDEN</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DEP_VEG</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>GNDWATR</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SURFWATR</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>GEO_X_SECT</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>PLAN_MAP</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>PHOTOS</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>PRECDATA</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>POLYGON</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LABTEST</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>REMARKS1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>REMARKS2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SOURCE1</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SOURCE2</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>NCGSINVS</attrlabl>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SM_Mech</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The classification of the slope movement mechanism</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Varnes (1978) and Cruden and Varnes (1996)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Blowout</edomv>
<edomvd>A type of slope failure in which water and material bursts forth from the ground and then proceeds downslope as overland flow.  Blowouts are possibly caused by excessive pore water pressure.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Hack and Goodlett, 1960</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Fall, Flow</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement shows components of both falling and flowing</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Slide, Fall</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement shows components of both sliding and falling</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Slide, Flow</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement shows components of both sliding and flowing</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Composite - Slide, Topple, Fall</edomv>
<edomvd>The slope movement shows components of sliding, toppling, and falling</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Fall</edomv>
<edomvd>A type of slope movement in which material abruptly breaks off or detaches from a steep slope or cliff surface. Little or no sliding (shear displacement) along the failure surface is involved, and the detached material descends mostly through the air by free fall, bouncing, or rolling.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Varnes, 1987</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Flow</edomv>
<edomvd>A type of slope movement in which the water content in the displaced mass is sufficient for the material to liquefy and behave as a viscous fluid.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Other - Creep</edomv>
<edomvd>The slow, more or less continuous downslope movement of mineral, rock, and soil particles by gravity.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Slide - General</edomv>
<edomvd>A slide in which the geometry of the failure surface is not obvious or known.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Slide - rotational</edomv>
<edomvd>A slide in which the displaced material experiences rotation (and characteristic backward tilting) as it progresses along a failure surface that is curved and concave upward.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Slide - translational</edomv>
<edomvd>A slide in which the displaced material experiences little to no rotation or backward tilting as it progresses downward along a failure surface that is typically planar.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SMD_Type</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The classification of a slope movement deposit.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Cruden and Varnes (1996)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Block field</edomv>
<edomvd>An accumulation of boulders or angular blocks of rock, generally with little or no fine sediment and without a cliff or a ledge upslope as an apparent source. Block fields usually occur on high mountain slopes where they are most extensive along slopes parallel to contour.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Block stream</edomv>
<edomvd>A linear accumulation of boulders or angular blocks of rock, generally with little or no fine sediment and without a cliff or a ledge upslope as an apparent source. Block streams usually occur at heads of ravines and as narrow bodies more extensive downslope than along slope.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Colluvium undifferentiated</edomv>
<edomvd>A general term applied to any loose, heterogeneous, and unconsolidated mass of soil and rock particles deposited by rainwash, sheetwash, mass wasting, or slow, continuous downslope creep. Colluvium usually contains angular to subrounded rock particles and usually collects at the base or other low gradient portions of slopes or hillsides.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Debris fan</edomv>
<edomvd>A deposit of debris-sized material that is known or reasonably inferred to be emplaced by mass wasting processes and has a distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape.  Debris fan can include colluvial and alluvial components.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Debris undifferentiated</edomv>
<edomvd>A deposit of debris sized material that is known or reasonably inferred to be emplaced by mass wasting processes but lacks the distinctive lobe, fan, or coalescing fan shape of a debris fan.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Talus</edomv>
<edomvd>Rock fragments of any size or shape, usually coarse and angular, derived from and lying at the base of a cliff or very steep rocky slope.  Talus is often a product of rockfall.</edomvd>
<edomvds>Cruden and Varnes, 1996</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>MvmtDate</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Calendar date of the slope movement in month, day, year data format where known.  If the complete date is not known, month and year of failure or just year of failure has been entered.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>calendar date</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Col_Date</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Calendar date the data was collected in month, day, year data format</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>calendar date</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>NC_Cnty</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The county name where the slope movement or slope movement deposit is located</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Buncombe</edomv>
<edomvd>State of North Carolina</edomvd>
<edomvds>State of North Carolina</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IZLatDD</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The latitude of the initiation zone of a slope movement in decimal degrees up to 6 decimal places if possible.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>35.43876</rdommin>
<rdommax>35.810062</rdommax>
<attrunit>Decimal Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IZLongDD</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The longitude of the initiation zone of a slope movement in decimal degrees up to 6 decimal places if possible.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>-82.842224</rdommin>
<rdommax>-82.17546</rdommax>
<attrunit>Decimal Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ApxLatDD</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The latitude of the centroid of a slope movement deposit in decimal degrees up to 6 decimal places if possible.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>35.42636</rdommin>
<rdommax>35.818843</rdommax>
<attrunit>Decimal Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>ApxLongDD</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The longitude of the centroid of a sloe movement deposit in decimal degrees up to 6 decimal places if possible.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>-82.877574</rdommin>
<rdommax>-82.182488</rdommax>
<attrunit>Decimal Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Road</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Road name and/or road number affected by or in close proximity to the slope movement or slope movement deposit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>NCDOT</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Road names and numbers</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Rd_Az</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Azimuth orientation of the road</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SA_Aspct</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The downslope aspect at the initiation zone of a slope movement</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Data_Src</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The source of data, example NCGS, USFS, EM-Swain County</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Entities that informed NCGS of the slope movement or slope movement deposit</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Loc_Conf</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Confidence in accuracy of latitude-longitude location of the slope movement or slope movement deposit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified - Dam Safety Personnel</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified by Dam Safety Personnel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified - Michalek</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified by Michalek</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified - NCDOT</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified by  NCDOT</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified - Pomeroy, Otteman</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified by Pomeroy and Otteman</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified - USFS</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified by the USFS</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified NCGS - 7.5' Quad</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified using USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle;  positional accuracy accurate within a 400-foot radius in the worst case</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified NCGS - Aerial Photo</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified using aerial photos; aerial photograph location accuracy varies, but is accurate within a 200-foot radius in the worst case</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified NCGS - GPS</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified using GPS with an accuracy within a 40-foot radius</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Field Verified NCGS - LiDAR</edomv>
<edomvd>field verified using LiDAR which is accurate within a 50-foot radius</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Not Field Verified - Aerial Photo</edomv>
<edomvd>located using aerial photography, but not field verified by NCGS staff</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Not Field Verified - Chuck Rankin</edomv>
<edomvd>located by Chuck Rankin, but not field verified by NCGS staff</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Not Field Verified - LiDAR</edomv>
<edomvd>located using LiDAR, but not field verified by NCGS staff</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Not Field Verified - Ron Nalley</edomv>
<edomvd>located by Ron Nalley, but not field verified by NCGS staff</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>EL_Head</attrlabl>
<attrdef>The elevation above mean sea level in feet determined from either USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle or from the LiDAR DEM of head of slope movement</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>1560</rdommin>
<rdommax>6000</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>EL_Toe</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the elevation above mean sea level in feet determined from either the USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle or from the LiDAR DEM of the toe of the slope movement or slope movement deposit.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>1530</rdommin>
<rdommax>5640</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Slp__Cnfg</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Configuration of slope on which movement or deposit occurred</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Cut Slope - Not Road Related</edomv>
<edomvd>A slope exposed by excavating earth materials not related to a roadway</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Embankment - Not Road Related</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil, rock fragments, and other materials put in place by humans and used to extend a side slope or a land surface for a roadway or building site, or to build up low-lying land, hold back water (e.g., dam), or fill in an enclosed space (e.g., mine workings).  Synonymous with man-made fill, but distinguished from naturally occurring, sedimentary fill.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>River Erosion</edomv>
<edomvd>Configuration formed through river erosional forces.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Road Cut</edomv>
<edomvd>A slope exposed by excavating earth material related to a roadway</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Road Embankment</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil, rock fragments, and other materials put in place by humans and used to extend a side slope or a land surface for a roadway or building site, or to build up low-lying land, hold back water (e.g., dam), or fill in an enclosed space (e.g., mine workings).  Synonymous with man-made fill, but distinguished from naturally occurring, sedimentary fill.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Unmodified</edomv>
<edomvd>A slope that has evolved naturally without any significant alteration by humans (includes timbering and farming, which are not considered significant slope modifying activities).</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>G_Pos</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative geomorphic position of the initiation zone of a slope movement. This is determined visually from the USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle or the LiDAR DEM by looking at the relative placement of the data point with respect to the top of the slope and the base of the slope.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Midslope</edomv>
<edomvd>Middle third of the slope that lies topographically below the upper slope and above the toe slope</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Ridge Top</edomv>
<edomvd>Thin, narrow crest of the hillside</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Toe Slope</edomv>
<edomvd>Lower third of the slope that lies topographically below the mid slope and above the flood plain</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Upper Slope</edomv>
<edomvd>Upper third of the slope that lies topographically below the ridge tope and above the midslope</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>G_Shape</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative geomorphic shape of the ground surface at the initiation zone of a slope movement.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Concave</edomv>
<edomvd>a slope that curves inward</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Convex</edomv>
<edomvd>a slope that curves outward</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Hollow</edomv>
<edomvd>a slope that is concave parallel and perpendicular to the slope</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Planar</edomv>
<edomvd>a slope that is flat and does not curve</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>G_Struct</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative geomorphic structure at the initiation zone of a slope movement.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Cruden, D.M. and Varnes, D.J., 1996</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Dip Slope</edomv>
<edomvd>dip direction of the slope is coincident (within + or - 15 degrees) to the dip direction of primary bedding or foliation of the bedrock</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Oblique Slope</edomv>
<edomvd>dip direction of the slope is at an oblique angle to the dip direction of primary bedding or foliation of the bedrock</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Scarp Slope</edomv>
<edomvd>dip direction of the slope is at an approximate 180-degree angle (within + or - 15 degrees) to the dip direction of primary bedding or foliation of the bedrock</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>D_Mass_L</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the estimated length in feet of the displaced mass of a slope movement or a slope movement deposit.  The estimate is made either visually while at the site or is scaled from an aerial photograph, USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle, or LiDAR DEM.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>8</rdommin>
<rdommax>230</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>D_Mass_W</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the estimated width in feet of the displaced mass of a slope movement measured at the initiation zone.  The estimate is made either visually while at the site or is scaled from an aerial photograph, USGS 7.5-minute topographic quadrangle, or LiDAR DEM</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>5</rdommin>
<rdommax>300</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>D_Mass_T</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the estimated thickness in feet of the displaced mass of a slope movement or a slope movement deposit.  The estimate is usually made visually while at the site.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>1</rdommin>
<rdommax>20</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>TrkLeng</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the length in feet of a debris flow or earth flow track from the head to the toe.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>26</rdommin>
<rdommax>4432</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Damage</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the text narrative of any damage or impacts of slope movement</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>written description</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Mvmt_His</attrlabl>
<attrdef>text narrative of movement history including dates, rates of movement if continued beyond initial date of movement, and information on any stabilization actions if known.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>written description</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Unit1985</attrlabl>
<attrdef>geologic map unit for the initiation point or apex as determined from the 1985 NCGS State Geologic Map</attrdef>
<attrdefs>1985 NCGS State Geologic Map</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>1985 NCGS State Geologic Map</codesetn>
<codesets>North Carolina Geologic Survey</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Othr_MU</attrlabl>
<attrdef>geologic map unit for the initiation point or apex as determined from various other geologic maps of the area</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Map unit from various map sources (see supplementary information)</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Srce_Veg</attrlabl>
<attrdef>General type of vegetation in the initiation zone of a slope movement based either on visual observation or from aerial photography.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>conifer forest</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by trees where 75 percent or more of the tree species maintain their leaves all year.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>deciduous forest</edomv>
<edomvd>reas dominated by trees where 75 percent or more of the tree species shed foliage simultaneously in response to seasonal change.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>grass-shrub</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by shrubs and upland grasses</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>grass-shrub-tree</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by shrubs, upland grasses and various tree species.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>mixed forest</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by trees where neither deciduous nor evergreen species represent more than 75 percent of the cover present.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>none</edomv>
<edomvd>No vegetation present at site.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>pavement-hard surface</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas characterized by a high percentage (30 percent or greater) of constructed materials</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>OrigGSl</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Slope in degrees of the original ground surface at the initiation zone. Abbreviations in parentheses indicate the location or type of slope where the measurement was taken (i.e., "e" for embankment, "c" for cut, "o" for original, undisturbed ground, "rflank" for right flank)</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>5</rdommin>
<rdommax>85</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith_1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Field classification of primary rock type at the initiation zone.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Rock type</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith_2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Field classification of secondary rock type at the initiation zone.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Rock type</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith_3</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Field classification of secondary or tertiary rock type at the initiation zone.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Rock type modifier</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith1Mod</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Textural and/or compositional modifier describing lithology unit 1</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Rock type modifier</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith2Mod</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Textural and/or compositional modifier describing lithology unit 2</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Rock type modifier</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith3Mod</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Textural and/or compositional modifier describing lithology unit 3</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Rock type modifier</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith1Mn1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Primary mineralogy from visual classification for lithology unit 1</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description - Mineralogy</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith1Mn2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Secondary mineralogy from visual classification for lithology 1</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description - Mineralogy</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith2Mn1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Secondary mineralogy from visual classification for lithology 1</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description - Mineralogy</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith2Mn2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Secondary mineralogy from visual classification for lithology 2</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description - Mineralogy</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith3Mn1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Primary mineralogy from visual classification for lithology 3</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description - Mineralogy</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Lith3Mn2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Secondary mineralogy from visual classification for lithology 3</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description - Mineralogy</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>URCS_1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unified rock classification of lithology 1</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>URCS_2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Unified rock classification of lithology 2</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>URCS__3</attrlabl>
<attrdef>United rock classification of lithology 3</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SulLith1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Visual estimate of relative percent of sulfides present in lithology 1</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Visual estimate of relative percent of sulfides present in lithology 1</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SulLith2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Visual estimate of relative percent of sulfides present in lithology 2</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Visual estimate of relative percent of sulfides present in lithology 2</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SulLith3</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Visual estimate of relative percent of sulfides present in lithology 3</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Visual estimate of relative percent of sulfides present in lithology 3</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Frac1AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a fracture/joint in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Frac1Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a fracture/joint in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Frac2AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a fracture/joint in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Frac2Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a fracture/joint in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Frac3AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a fracture/joint in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Frac3Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a fracture/joint in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BRFltAZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a brittle fault/fault zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BRFltDip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a brittle fault/fault zone in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>BRFltThk</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Approximate thickness of a brittle fault/fault zone in feet.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>0</rdommax>
<attrunit>feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DLFltAZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a ductile fault/fault zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DLFltDip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a ductile fault/fault zone in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>DLFltThk</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Approximate thickness of a ductile fault/fault zone in feet</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>0</rdommax>
<attrunit>Feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SLBrg</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Bearing of slickenlines measured on a brittle fault</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SLPlunge</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Plunge of slickenlines measured on a brittle fault</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Fol1AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a foliation in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Fol1Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a foliation in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Fol2AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a foliation in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Fol2Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a foliation in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Fol3AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of a foliation in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Fol3Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of a foliation in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CL1AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of compositional layering in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CL1Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of compositional layering in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CL2AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of compositional layering in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>CL2Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of compositional layering in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Bdg1AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of bedding in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Bdg1Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of bedding in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Bdg2AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of bedding in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Bdg2Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of bedding in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of bedding in the initiation zone</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IC1AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of an intrusive contact in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IC1Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of an intrusive contact in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IC2AZ</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured strike in azimuth degrees of an intrusive contact in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>360</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>IC2Dip</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Measured dip of an intrusive contact in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>90</rdommax>
<attrunit>Degrees</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Other_SD</attrlabl>
<attrdef>other pertinent structural data that either does not have a predetermined category in the database or should be included for clarification purposes</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Description of other pertinent structural data that either does not have a predetermined category in the database or should be included for clarification purposes</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1Orgn</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Origin of the primary soil/sediment in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>colluvium</edomv>
<edomvd>A general term applied to any loose, heterogeneous, and unconsolidated mass of soil and rock particles deposited by rainwash, sheetwash, mass wasting, or slow, continuous downslope creep. Colluvium usually contains angular to subrounded rock particles and usually collects at the base or other low gradient portions of slopes or hillsides.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1987)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>residuum</edomv>
<edomvd>An unconsolidated or partly weathered, parent material soil, that developed in place by the physical and chemical weathering from the consolidated rock on which it lies.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>fill</edomv>
<edomvd>Man-placed deposits of natural earth materials.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1987)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>alluvium</edomv>
<edomvd>Clay, silt, sand, gravel or similar unconsolidated detrital earthen material deposited during relatively recent geologic time by a stream or other body of running water. Alluvium usually contains rounded particles and usually collects in the channels and floodplains of creeks, streams, rivers, and lakes.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1987)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1Struc</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative overall textural classification of soil unit 1/primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Clast Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>A soil in which the majority is composed of coarse-grained rock masses that are in direct contact with one another</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Matrix Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is composed of coarse-grained rock fragments suspended in fine-grained soil, and the rock fragments are not typically in direct contact with one another.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1ASTM</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1Mtrx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of the fine-grained matrix of soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1MClr</attrlabl>
<attrdef>matrix color of soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>basic color description of soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1MClSz</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Maximum size of the coarse-grained portion of soil unit one or the primary soil measured in feet</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>.1</rdommin>
<rdommax>10</rdommax>
<attrunit>feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1ClShp</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the degree of abraision of a clastic particle as shown by the sharpness of its edges and corners for soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>angluar</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles have sharp edges and relatively plane sides with unpolished surfaces</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>round</edomv>
<edomvd>The particles are rounded with polished surfaces</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>round-subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between round and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles are similar to angular description but have rounded edges</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subangularand angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subround and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround-subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subround and subangular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1ClLi</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit one or the primary soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1ClWx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general degree of weathering of rock fragments in soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1Thick</attrlabl>
<attrdef>approximate thickness of the soil unit one or the primary soil in feet; value may be a single number or an estimated range of soil thickness</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>General thickness of soil in feet</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl1RelDen</attrlabl>
<attrdef>relative consistency or compactness of soil unit one or the primary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Dense</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil must be loosened with pick to excavate with a hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Hard</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil can be indented with thumbnail with difficulty</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Loose</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is easily excavated with hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Medium</edomv>
<edomvd>soil can be penetrated with thumb but with great effort</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Soft</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is indented with fist and/or penetrated easily with thumb</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Very Stiff</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is readily indented with thumbnail</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2Orgn</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Origin of the secondary soil/sediment in the initiation zone</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>colluvium</edomv>
<edomvd>A general term applied to any loose, heterogeneous, and unconsolidated mass of soil and rock particles deposited by rainwash, sheetwash, mass wasting, or slow, continuous downslope creep. Colluvium usually contains angular to subrounded rock particles and usually collects at the base or other low gradient portions of slopes or hillsides.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1987)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>fill</edomv>
<edomvd>Man-placed deposits of natural earth materials.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1987)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>residuum</edomv>
<edomvd>An unconsolidated or partly weathered, parent material soil, that developed in place by the physical and chemical weathering from the consolidated rock on which it lies.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2Struc</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative overall textural classification of soil unit two or the secondary soil; options include the following</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Clast Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>A soil in which the majority is composed of coarse-grained rock masses that are in direct contact with one another.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Matrix Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is composed of coarse-grained rock fragments suspended in fine-grained soil, and the rock fragments are not typically in direct contact with one another.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2ASTM</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2Mtrx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of the fine-grained matrix of soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2MClr</attrlabl>
<attrdef>matrix color of soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>basic color description of soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2MClSz</attrlabl>
<attrdef>maximum size of the coarse-grained portion of soil unit two or the secondary soil measured in feet</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>.2</rdommin>
<rdommax>2</rdommax>
<attrunit>feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2ClShp</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the degree of abraision of a clastic particle as shown by the sharpness of its edges and corners for soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>angular</edomv>
<edomvd>particles have sharp edges and relatively plane sides with unpolished surfaces</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>particles are similar to angular description but have rounded edges</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2ClLi</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit two or the secondary soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2ClWx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general degree of weathering of rock fragments in soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2Thick</attrlabl>
<attrdef>approximate thickness of the soil unit two or the secondary soil in feet; value may be a single number or an estimated range of soil thickness</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>General thickness of soil in feet</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl2RelDen</attrlabl>
<attrdef>relative consistency or compactness of soil unit two or the secondary soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Compact</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is difficult to excavate with a hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Loose</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is easily excavated with hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3Orgn</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Origin of the primary soil/sediment in the deposit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>colluvium</edomv>
<edomvd>A general term applied to any loose, heterogeneous, and unconsolidated mass of soil and rock particles deposited by rainwash, sheetwash, mass wasting, or slow, continuous downslope creep. Colluvium usually contains angular to subrounded rock particles and usually collects at the base or other low gradient portions of slopes or hillsides.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1997)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3Struc</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative overall textural classification of soil unit three or the primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Clast Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>A soil in which the majority is composed of coarse-grained rock masses that are in direct contact with one another</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Bates and Jackson (1997)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Matrix Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>A soil composed of coarse-grained rock fragments suspended in fine-grained soil</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Bates and Jackson (1997)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3ASTM</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of soil unit three or the primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3Mtrx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of the fine-grained matrix of soil unit three or the primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>ASTM classification of the fine-grained matrix of soil unit three or the primary deposit soil</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3MClr</attrlabl>
<attrdef>matrix color of soil unit three or the primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>basic color description of soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3MClSz</attrlabl>
<attrdef>maximum size of the coarse-grained portion of soil unit three or the primary deposit soil measured in feet</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>.3</rdommin>
<rdommax>40</rdommax>
<attrunit>feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3ClShp</attrlabl>
<attrdef>the degree of abraision of a clastic particle as shown by the sharpness of its edges and corners for soil unit three or the primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles have sharp edges and relatively plane sides with unpolished surfaces</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>round-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between round and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>round-subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between round and subangular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles are similar to angular description but have rounded edges</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subangular and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles have nearly plane sides but have well-rounded corners and edges</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subround and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround-subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subround and subangular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3ClLi</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit 3/primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit 3/primary deposit soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3ClWx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general degree of weathering of rock fragments in soil unit 3/primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3Thick</attrlabl>
<attrdef>approximate thickness of the soil unit 3/primary deposit soil in feet; value may be a single number or an estimated range of soil thickness</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>General thickness of soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl3RelDen</attrlabl>
<attrdef>relative consistency or compactness of soil unit 3/primary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Compact</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is difficult to excavate with a hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Loose</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is easily excavated with hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Soft</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is indented with fist and/or penetrated easily with thumb</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Very Stiff</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is readily indented with thumbnail</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Medium</edomv>
<edomvd>soil can be penetrated with thumb but with great effort</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4Orgn</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Origin of the secondary soil/sediment in the deposit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>colluvium</edomv>
<edomvd>Any loose, heterogeneous, and unconsolidated mass of soil and rock particles deposited by rainwash, sheetwash, or slow, continuous downslope creep. Colluvium usually contains angular to subrounded rock particles and usually collects at the base or other low gradient portions of slopes or hillsides.</edomvd>
<edomvds>NCGS based on Jackson (1997)</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4Struc</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Relative overall textural classification of soil unit 4/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Clast Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>a soil in which the majority is composed of coarse-grained rock masses that are in direct contact with one another</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Matrix Supported</edomv>
<edomvd>a soil composed of coarse-grained rock fragments suspended in fine-grained soil</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4ASTM</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Classification of soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4Mtrx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>ASTM classification of the fine-grained matrix of soil unit 4/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Annual Book of Standards - Soils</codesetn>
<codesets>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4MClr</attrlabl>
<attrdef>matrix color of soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>basic color description of soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4MClSz</attrlabl>
<attrdef>maximum size of the coarse-grained portion of soil unit four/secondary deposit soil measured in feet</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>0</rdommax>
<attrunit>feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4ClShp</attrlabl>
<attrdef>angularity of the coarse-grained portion of soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles have sharp edges and relatively plane sides with unpolished surfaces</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>round-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between round and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>round-subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between round and subangular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles are similar to angular description but have rounded edges</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subangular-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subangular and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround-angular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subround and angular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>subround-subangular</edomv>
<edomvd>Particles with a range of angularity between subround and subangular</edomvd>
<edomvds>ASTM 2488-84, 1984</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4ClLi</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>general rock classification of rock fragments in soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4ClWx</attrlabl>
<attrdef>general degree of weathering of rock fragments in soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>Williamson (1984)</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<codesetd>
<codesetn>Unified Rock Classification System</codesetn>
<codesets>Williamson (1984)</codesets>
</codesetd>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4Thick</attrlabl>
<attrdef>approximate thickness of the soil unit four/secondary deposit soil in feet; value may be a single number or an estimated range of soil thickness</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<rdom>
<rdommin>0</rdommin>
<rdommax>0</rdommax>
<attrunit>feet</attrunit>
</rdom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Sl4RelDen</attrlabl>
<attrdef>relative consistency or compactness of soil unit four/secondary deposit soil</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Loose</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is easily excavated with hand shovel</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>soft</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil is indented with fist and/or penetrated easily with thumb</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Dep_Veg</attrlabl>
<attrdef>General type of vegetation on the deposit based on visual observation or aerial photograph</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Deciduous Forest</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by trees where 75 percent or more of the treAreas dominated by trees where 75 percent or more of the tree species maintain their leaves all year.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>grass-shrub</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by shrubs and upland grasses</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Grass-shrub-tree</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by shrubs, upland grasses and various tree species.</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Mixed Forest</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by trees where neither deciduous nor evergreen species represent more than 75 percent of the cover present.</edomvd>
<edomvds>USGS</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>pavement-hard surface</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominanted by pavement or another hard surface</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>mixed grass-crop-forest</edomv>
<edomvd>Areas dominated by natural or semi-natural grass, various tree species, and areas used for production of crops</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>GndWatr</attrlabl>
<attrdef>description of the groundwater conditions at the initiation zone of a slope movement or the apex of a slope movement deposit if known</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Bedrock Seep/Spring</edomv>
<edomvd>groundwater is discharging in the bedrock along one or more discontinuities</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>None Observed</edomv>
<edomvd>no evidence of groundwater was observed at the site</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Soil-Sediment &amp; Bedrock Seep/Spring</edomv>
<edomvd>groundwater is discharging along the contact between the bedrock and the overlying soil</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Soil-Sediment Seep/Spring</edomv>
<edomvd>Groundwater is discharging within the soil/sediment</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SurfWatr</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Description of the surface water conditions at the initiation zone of a slope movement or the apex of a slope movement deposit if known</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Modified slope drainage into SM</edomv>
<edomvd>the natural ground conditions have been modified so that surface water is directed onto the slope movement</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Natural drainage into SM</edomv>
<edomvd>the natural ground conditions direct surface water onto the slope movement</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>None Observed</edomv>
<edomvd>no surface water was observed at the site</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Road drainage into SM</edomv>
<edomvd>drainage from a road flows onto the slope movement</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Geo_X_Sect</attrlabl>
<attrdef>indication of whether or not a geologic cross-section has been constructed for that location</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>yes</edomv>
<edomvd>geologic cross section has been constructed</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>no</edomv>
<edomvd>geologic cross section has not been constructed</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Plan_Map</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Indication of whether or not a plan map has been constructed for that location</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Yes</edomv>
<edomvd>plan map constructed</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>No</edomv>
<edomvd>plan map not constructed</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Surve</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Photos</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Indication of whether or not photos have been taken of that location</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Yes</edomv>
<edomvd>Photos have been taken</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>No</edomv>
<edomvd>Photos have not been taken</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>PrecData</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Indication of whether or not precipitation data is available for that location at the time of the slope failure</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Yes</edomv>
<edomvd>Precipitation data is available</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>No</edomv>
<edomvd>No precipitation data available</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Polygon</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Indication of whether or not a polygon has been drawn in a shape file representing the extent of the slope movement or slope movement deposit.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Yes</edomv>
<edomvd>A polygon has been drawn</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>No</edomv>
<edomvd>A polygon has not been drawn</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>LabTest</attrlabl>
<attrdef>indication of type of testing performed on material in a slope movement or slope movement deposit.  If field is left blank, no testing was performed at that location.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<edom>
<edomv>Soil Test</edomv>
<edomvd>Soil tests were performed on samples from this location</edomvd>
<edomvds>North Carolina Geological Survey</edomvds>
</edom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Remarks1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>text narrative of any additional information pertinent to entry including but not limited to detailed rock descriptions, location descriptions, velocity and discharge estimates, etc</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>text narrative</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Remarks2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>text narrative of any additional information pertinent to entry including but not limited to detailed rock descriptions, location descriptions, velocity and discharge estimates, etc</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>text narrative</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Source1</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Full citation of the primary literature source used to obtain information about the slope movement or slope movement deposit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>text narrative</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>Source2</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Full citation of the secondary literature source used to obtain information about the slope movement or slope movement deposit</attrdef>
<attrdefs>North Carolina Geological Survey</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>text narrative</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
<attr>
<attrlabl>SHAPE</attrlabl>
<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
<attrdomv>
<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
</attrdomv>
</attr>
</detailed>
</eainfo>
<distinfo>
<distrib>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>North Carolina Geologic Survey</cntorg>
<cntper>Richard M. Wooten</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>Senior Geologist for Geohazards and Engineering Geology</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2090 U.S. 70 Highway</address>
<city>Swannanoa</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>28778</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>828.296.4500 ext.4632</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>none</cnttdd>
<cntfax>828.299.7043</cntfax>
<cntemail>Rick.Wooten@ncdenr.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1700 eastern</hours>
<cntinst>Prefer initial contact by e-mail, followed by voice contact.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</distrib>
<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
<distliab>The North Carolina Department of Environment and Natural Resources (NCDENR), North Carolina Geological Survey (NCGS) is charged by the State of North Carolina to develop landslide hazard assessment maps for the Blue Ridge region of western North Carolina.  NCGS is committed to offering its users accurate, useful, and current information.  All electronic and/or hardcopy products (maps, data, and text, etc.) produced by this landslide hazard assessment program are considered public information (unless otherwise noted) and may be distributed or copied.  These products, however, are intended to serve for general planning purposes only, and are provided on an "as is" basis. USE OF THESE MATERIALS CONSTITUTES ACCEPTANCE OF THIS DISCLAIMER OF LIABILITY.  Therefore, the client must be aware of data conditions and bear responsibility for the appropriate use of the information with respect to possible errors, original map scale, collection methodology, currency of data, and other conditions specific to certain data. The user must be cautious when using these data, as none of the data represented here are perfect.  Also, as in many complex scientific endeavors, error can be expected.  In no event shall NCDENR, NCGS, or its employees be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental, special, exemplary, or consequential damages (including, but not limited to, procurement or substitute goods or services; loss of use, data, or profits; or business interruption) however caused and on any theory of liability, whether in contract, strict liability, or tort (including negligence or otherwise) arising in any way out of the use of these data, even if advised of the possibility of such damage.</distliab>
<stdorder>
<digform>
<digtinfo>
<transize>0.034</transize>
</digtinfo>
</digform>
</stdorder>
<custom>All data is available through standard ordering procedures on a cost recovery basis.</custom>
<techpreq>All formats supplied are created using ESRI ArcGIS 9.2 GIS software. Other formats are available per request. Format compatibility is the user's responsibility.</techpreq>
</distinfo>
<metainfo>
<metd>20100909</metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>North Carolina Geological Survey</cntorg>
<cntper>Anne Carter Witt</cntper>
</cntorgp>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2090 U.S. 70 Highway</address>
<city>Swannanoa</city>
<state>NC</state>
<postal>28778</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>828.296.4500 ext. 4637</cntvoice>
<cnttdd>none</cnttdd>
<cntfax>828.299.7043</cntfax>
<cntemail>anne.witt@ncdenr.gov</cntemail>
<hours>0800 - 1700 eastern</hours>
<cntinst>Prefer initial contact by e-mail, followed by voice contact.</cntinst>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
<mettc>local time</mettc>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
<metextns>
<onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
<metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
</metextns>
</metainfo>
</metadata>
